Guide to the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation oral histories 2008.030
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Robinson, Annette, 2008 February 1; 2008.030.36
  Assemblywoman Annette Robinson was born in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan and raised in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. She received both her bachelor's and master's degrees from New Hampshire College. A member of the Democratic Party, much of Robinson's adult life was spent in public service. In 1977, she was elected to the Community School Board of District 16, where she served three terms. She served six years in the administration of former New York City comptroller Harrison J. Goldin, and afterward became the District Director for U.S. Congressman Major R. Owens. Robinson was elected to the New York City Council in 1991 as a representative of the 36th district; and in 2002 assumed office in the New York State Assembly. There she represented District 56, which includes most of Bedford-Stuyvesant, along with the Crown Heights and Bushwick neighborhoods of Brooklyn. Robinson had six children and was married for over fifty years to William Robinson (deceased).
  In this interview, Assemblywoman Annette Robinson speaks of her long ties to Restoration, and the impact it's had on the local community. She reminisces about the idyllic Bedford-Stuyvesant of her youth, during a time when the community was protective of its children, and neighbors closely watched community goings-on. Robinson describes the necessity of programs that increase children's sense of self-worth and personal expectations, particularly those in the arts and education, and workforce development and jobs training for teenagers. Robinson maintains close ties with a number of international municipalities; for instance in Brazil, Panama, and South Africa. She describes the importance of cooperative learning programs in uncovering novel solutions to shared problems. At the interview's end, Robinson reflects on her motivations as a politician, and reveals that her original life dream was to be a professional dancer. Interview conducted by Bahati Williams.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brazil; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Enterprise zones |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (State) |x Politics and government; South Africa; Bedford-Stuyvesant Development and Services Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Robinson, Annette (Annette M.); Vann, Albert
- Robinson, James, 2008 January 15; 2008.030.37
  James Robinson was born in 1937 and moved to the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn circa 1944, when Robinson was seven years old; he attended local Brooklyn public schools. In the mid-1960s, Robinson first encountered Restoration when Robinson served as the Director of Urban Renewal of Fulton Park. In 1978, when Restoration's vice president of physical development, James E. Shipp, stepped down, Robinson was retained as Shipp's successor. Robinson served as the vice president of physical development into the early 1980s.
  In this interview, James Robinson recites the many roles of Restoration in the community of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. Robinson says Restoration's successes in community development are evident in the gentrification that has swept through the neighborhood, but voices dismay at the displacement this has caused for some indigenous residents. Robinson describes an idyllic Brooklyn childhood, with public school students competitive for grades in the classroom and for points on the playground; and remembers teachers comporting themselves with authority and dignity, and a time when parents commanded respect. Robinson details his first interactions with Restoration and his eventual position as its vice president of physical development (succeeding James E. Shipp). He lists key leaders, community organizations, and funding organizations who helped during his tenure, and names a number of accomplishments of which he believes Restoration should be proud. He describes the practice of redlining, saying Restoration combatted the practice, making it easier for residents of Bedford-Stuyvesant to get loans. Robinson says physical development alone is not sufficient in a community's development, but should be accompanied by arts education, cultural activities, and encouragement for entrepreneurs. Interview conducted by Doris Rowley-Hoyte.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation. Center for Art and Culture; Billie Holiday Theatre; Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Robinson, James E.
- Sanford, Adelaide, 2008 January 24; 2008.030.38
  Dr. Regent Adelaide Sanford, born in 1925, was a career educator notable for her fiery defense of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn's African American students, and her unanimous election to the Board of Regents of the State University of New York. Sanford received her BeD degree from Brooklyn College in 1947, and her MeD degree from Wellesley College in 1950. After fifteen years as a school teacher in New York City's elementary schools, Sanford became assistant principal, and later principal, at Crispus Attucks School in Brooklyn. She earned her PhD degree from Fordham University in 1967. Sanford won unanimous election to the Board of Regents of the State University of New York in 1986. Throughout her tenure, Sanford's interest lay primarily in elevating the achievements and standards of low-performing schools.
  In this four-hour interview, Dr. Regent Adelaide Sanford discusses her life's history, beginning with her recollection of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1930s and during the Great Depression, and recounts a number of personal stories involving segregation and Jim Crow laws. Sanford recalls the foundation of Restoration, including its early effects on the neighborhood's African American citizens. Throughout the interview, Sanford openly discusses her personal opinions about the state of race in America in 2008, her achievements as an activist, and the reasons she was particularly successful. She shares her thoughts on her tenure with the Board of Regents, Ebonics in schools, the 2008 U.S. presidential election, and corruption in politics. Sanford discusses her personal life; her courtship and marriage, her diagnosis of and treatment for breast cancer, her affection for the African country of Ghana (where she was crowned a Queen Mother), and her Christian religious beliefs. Interview conducted by Laurie Cumbo and Sady Sullivan.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African diaspora; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Black nationalism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education; Museums; New York (N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Religion |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Segregation |z United States; United States |x History; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Sanford, Adelaide; University of the State of New York
- Shiffman, Ronald, 2008 February 4; 2008.030.39
  Ron Shiffman was born in 1938 in Israel. His parents had immigrated to Israel from Russia after his father was imprisoned in a Siberian gulag for his expression of Zionist political views. Shiffman's parents later immigrated to the Bronx borough of New York City, where Shiffman grew up. Shiffman graduated from Pratt Institute's School of Architecture, and later its School of Urban Planning. In 1964, Shiffman co-founded the Pratt Institute Center for Community and Environmental Development (now known as the Pratt Center for Community Development). In 1965, Shiffman, in partnership with the Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council and Senator Robert F. Kennedy, conceived and launched the first community development corporation, known today as the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation. In 2012, Shiffman won the Jane Jacobs medal for Lifetime Achievement from the Rockefeller Foundation.
  In this interview, Ron Shiffman remembers the nascence of what became Restoration. He provides background information, tells of its involvement with the Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council, which spearheaded its initial plan, and their fated introduction to U.S. Senator Robert F. Kennedy. Shiffman recounts Kennedy's historic tour of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn; the founding of the Bedford-Stuyvesant Renewal and Rehabilitation Corporation and the schism that birthed Restoration. Shiffman provides his opinion on the role that racism, sexism, and classism played in Bedford-Stuyvesant politics of the 1960s. Shiffman discusses the problems with reliance on federal funding for community development corporations (CDCs), and discusses Restoration's succession of presidents, noting their individual legacies. Shiffman discusses his work as a consultant to CDCs worldwide, particularly in South Africa. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan with Kate Fermoile.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Black nationalism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; City planning |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; South Africa; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Kennedy, Robert F.; Pratt Institute; Shiffman, Ron
- Shipp, James, 2008 January 11; 2008.030.40
  James E. Shipp (born 1941) grew up in Illinois, where he attended high school and graduated with a bachelor's degree from Western Illinois University in 1964. He earned a master's degree in city and regional planning from Pratt Institute in Brooklyn, and a master's degree in urban studies from Occidental College. After his studies, Shipp worked as a youth gang counselor in Chicago's juvenile justice system, where he developed an interest in community economic development as a way to fight juvenile delinquency. Shipp's involvement in a Ford Foundation-funded training program led to a mentorship under Franklin Thomas, and eventually to his role with Restoration in Brooklyn. Shipp served as Restoration's first vice president, from its inception in 1969 through 1979. After leaving Restoration, Shipp served as the chief executive officer of Cummins Metropower, the distribution and service arm of Cummins Engine Company, a manufacturer of diesel engines.
  In this interview, James E. Shipp provides a short biography of his professional career, beginning with his time as a youth gang counselor in Chicago's juvenile justice system. He describes the realization that juvenile delinquency is caused by dysfunctional community systems, and his determination to build healthier urban communities. Shipp details his path to Restoration; laying out Restoration's essential role and functions. Shipp details Restoration's evolution as an institution, lists its successes in human and capital investment, and advocates for the confinement of its activities to housing renovation and commercial development. At the interview's end, Shipp reflects on Restoration's legacy and major successes, and gives an optimistic prognosis of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn's economic future. Interview conducted by Judith Anglin.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 21st century; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Discrimination in mortgage loans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Mortgages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Shipp, James E.; Thomas, Franklin A.
- Solano, Juan, 2008 May 15; 2008.030.41
  Juan Solano, born 1952, was the proprietor and optician at Solano Optical. Solano's first job out of high school was as a shipping clerk for a local optician. From age eighteen to age forty, Solano worked at a large variety of optical retailers, where he learned the business, eventually earning his bachelor's degree and becoming a licensed optician. At the age of forty-two, Solano and his wife took a second mortgage on their home, and used the money to open the first Solano Optical. At the time of the 2008 interview, Solano and his wife had recently purchased their own building, which included a storefront and residential rental property.
  In this interview, Juan Solano, owner of Solano Optical, reflects on his personal journey as an entrepreneur, which began with his first job as a shipping clerk at an optician's office and ended with the purchase of a mixed-use building which provided Solano a stable storefront, residential rental income, and a family home. At some points, Solano becomes emotional as he describes his experiences, including ups and downs such as the loss of five different stores due to rising rents, non-renewed leases, and recession. Solano describes the United States healthcare system as broken, citing the managed care system as a chief example. He speaks at length about his own lenses, which are transition bifocals. Solano voices his experiences with major crime: scuffles with illegal vendors of counterfeit and stolen goods; being victimized by gang activity; and suffering an armed robbery. Near the interview's end, Solano discusses the perks of membership in the Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants Association and other forms of leadership in the local business community. In the final minutes, Solano intolerantly refers to the nearby Hasidic Jewish community. Interview conducted by Bahati Williams.
  Bankruptcy |z New York (State) |z New York; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Enterprise zones |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Entrepreneurship |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Medical care |z United States; New York (N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Storefronts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants Association; Solano, Juan; Solano Optical Boutique Ltd
- Southerland, Eva, 2008 May 5; 2008.030.42
  A native of Florida, Eva Southerland's eleven-year tenure of employment with Restoration began in 1968, and capped off her life's career in non-profits. While employed by Restoration, Southerland worked in a number of different departments, including administration, finance, development, and outreach. At the time of the 2008 interview, Southerland had retired and lived in the East Flatbush neighborhood of Brooklyn with her husband, John Southerland.
  In this interview, Eva Southerland describes her early life in Florida, her move to New York City, and eventual move to Brooklyn in search of affordable housing. She details her career in non-profits. Southerland recalls the positions she served at Restoration, its work culture, and the organization after the retirement of corporation president Franklin Thomas. She shares her thoughts on Restoration's longevity; discusses its outreach programming for housing, children, and arts education; and evaluates its impact on the community of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; East Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Development and Services Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Kennedy, Robert F.; Southerland, Eva; Thomas, Franklin A.
- Southerland, John, 2008 May 5; 2008.030.43
  John Southerland, born in 1939 in Sanford, North Carolina, moved to Brooklyn, New York, in 1964 to secure steady employment. He worked in police communication for twenty-seven years before retiring and moonlighting as a private taxi driver. Southerland met his wife, Eva, an employee of Restoration, as he regularly would drive her home in his taxi.
  In this interview, John Southerland discusses his 1964 relocation from North Carolina to New York City in search of employment and his wife Eva Southerland's involvement with Restoration. Southerland observes the changes to the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn; in particular, rising housing costs. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.); Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Youth in Action; Billie Holiday Theatre; Kennedy, Robert F.; Southerland, John; Thomas, Franklin A.
- Stanton-Gilkes, Delwyn, 2008 May 14; 2008.030.44
  At the time of the 2008 interview, Delwyn Stanton-Gilkes was the resident African drumming instructor at Restoration's Youth Arts Academy.
  In this short interview, Delwyn Stanton-Gilkes describes the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn; its residents, culture, and changes -- such as gentrification and racial mixing -- brought on by economic development. He discusses his life's association with Restoration's Youth Arts Academy, and the impact it's had on his life. Interview conducted by Anasa Scott.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Dancers |z New York (State) |z New York; East Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Musicians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Performing arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Stanton-Gilkes, Delwyn; Youth Arts Academy
- Thomas, Franklin, 2008 February 1; 2008.030.45
  Born in 1934, Franklin Thomas grew up in and attended public schools in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. He attended Columbia University for both undergraduate and law school. After spending four years with the United States Air Force, Thomas' early career was spent as deputy legal counsel for the New York Police Department; this position led to his appointment as the Executive Director of Restoration. Thomas was President and Chief Executive Officer of the Ford Foundation from 1979 to 1996.
  In this interview, Franklin Thomas discusses the inception and early years of Restoration. He evaluates the unique nature of Restoration and its ideals as an organization. Thomas judges the importance of community involvement in Restoration specifically and the role of community development corporations. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Philanthropists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Shiffman, Ron; Thomas, Franklin A.
- Thompson, William C., Sr., 2008 May 5; 2008.030.46
  Honorable William C. Thompson, Sr., born 1924 in New York City, was among the founding members of Restoration. He was the first African American New York State Senator, and served as a Justice of the New York State Supreme Court.
  In this interview, Honorable William C. Thompson, Sr., discusses the founding and earliest days of Restoration. He recalls his colleagues Franklin Thomas and Robert F. Kennedy. Justice Thompson evaluates the difference between Restoration and other community organizations (namely, that Restoration did not operate under the aegis of the Office of Economic Opportunity). He recounts Restoration's efforts in job creation and describes changes occurring in Brooklyn and the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, circa 2008. At the interview's end, Thompson reminisces about his early life and the Brooklyn neighborhoods he has called home, including Brooklyn Heights. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Youth in Action; Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel); Kennedy, Robert F.; Thomas, Franklin A.; Thompson, William C., Sr., Hon.
- Valdes, Patricia, 2008 May 15; 2008.030.47
  Patricia Valdes worked as a coordinator for the Board of Elections at a senior citizens' site. While working one Election Day, Valdes learned of Restoration's Weatherization Program, which aids area citizens whose homes are unable to retain heat, or who are unable to afford heating during the wintertime. Because Valdes' home suffered from significant disrepair that made her home dangerous to inhabit, Restoration's Weatherization Program performed home renovations to rectify her situation.
  In this interview, Patricia Valdes and Wendell Rice discuss the substantial repairs performed on Valdes' home by Restoration's Weatherization Program. Valdes details her home's condition prior to repair and discusses her experience with the Weatherization Program, from the application process through the completion of construction. Valdes was unable to afford the repairs, which were appraised at over twenty thousand dollars. Restoration's Weatherization Program performed this work; which included the installation of a new roof, its insulation, removal of her neighbor's chimney which had fallen onto her property, installation of two windows, air sealing, hot-water wrapping, and upgrading of her water boiler. Interview conducted by Wendell Rice.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Maintenance and repair; Home economics |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Home ownership |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Valdes, Patricia
- Vann, Albert, 2008 April 10; 2008.030.48